Guide to the Dorothy Richardson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dorothy Richardson collection
1889-1967
GEN MSS 302
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.2
(11 boxes)
Correspondence by, to, and about Dorothy Richardson, with manuscripts of her short stories, articles and novels, as well as other writings about Richardson. Accompanied by clippings of articles by and about Richardson and her friends, legal agreements, and photographs. Principal correspondents include John and Ruby Austen, Bernice Elliott, Peggy Kirkaldy, Alan and Rose Odle, Phyllis Playter and John Cowper Powys, Henry Savage, and H. G. Wells.
Richardson, Dorothy M. (Dorothy Miller), 1873-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Dorothy Richardson Collection was established in 1958 by the gift of letters, manuscripts, annotated books and photographs from her sister-in-law, Mrs. Rose Odle. Additional gifts have been made by Mrs. John Austen, Bryher, Bernice Elliott, John Cowper Powys, Mrs. Harold Tomkinson, and others.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Many materials have been microfilmed. Consult the Public Service Desk for further information.
Scope and Contents
Dorothy Miller Richardson, 1873-1957
(Mrs. Alan Odle)
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I. CORRESPONDENCE
Letters by Dorothy Richardson
Letters to Dorothy Richardson
Letters by others, mostly about Dorothy Richardson
Series II. WRITINGS
Miscellaneous
MSS and typescripts of Dorothy Richardson's works
MSS and typescripts of works about Dorothy Richardson
Series III. SPECIAL FILES
Clippings of articles by Dorothy Richardson
Clippings about Dorothy Richardson
Clippings about Dorothy Richardson's works
Clippings about other people connected with Dorothy Richardson
Legal agreements
Photographs
Novelists, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Novelists -- England; Austen, John; Austen, Ruby; Elliott, Bernice; Kirkaldy, Peggy; Odle, Alan; Odle, Rose; Playter, Phyllis; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963; Richardson, Dorothy M. (Dorothy Miller), 1873-1957; Savage, Henry, Jr., 1903-1990; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946
- Correspondence, 1902-64; Series I; 2.6; (7 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Letters by Dorothy Richardson are arranged alphabetically by recipient. Letters to Dorothy Richardson are arranged alphabetically by author. Letters by others, mostly about Dorothy Richardson are arranged alphabetically by author, then by recipient.
  - LETTERS BY DOROTHY RICHARDSON TO:
    - Unidentified ("W.F."), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      1 letter. With a drawing by Alan Odle & 2 photocopies
    - Austen, Ruby & John, 1924-50 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      60 letters. With correspondence between Ruby Austen & Norman Holmes Pearson
    - Austen, Ruby & John, 1924-50 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      60 letters. Typed copies of the letters in folder 2
    - Brome, Mr., 1950 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      1 letter. 2 typed copies
    - Church, Richard, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      2 letters
    - Elliott, Bernice, 1927-52 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      55 letters & 13 postcards
    - Elliott, Bernice, 1927-52 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      34 letters. Typed copies
    - Garnett, Edward, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      1 letter
    - Gawsworth, John, 1932-4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      6 letters. With 3 envelopes
    - Jones, E.B.C., 1929-39 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      22 letters. Typed copies
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy, 1928-31 (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
      262 letters & 95 postcards
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy, 1932-45 (Box 2, Folder 18-28)
      262 letters & 95 postcards (cont.)
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy, 1946-52 (Box 3, Folder 29-32)
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy, 1928-40 (Box 3, Folder 33-38)
      259 letters. Typed copies.
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy, 1941-52 (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
      259 letters. Typed copies (cont.)
    - Kumar, Shiv K., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      1 letter & 1 postcard. Typed copies
    - Marrian, Pauline, 1945-52 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      9 letters. Typed copies
    - Morgan, Louise, 1926-50 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      6 letters. Typed copies
    - Odle, Alan, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      5 letters
    - Odle, Rose, 1948-52 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      28 letters & 1 postcard. With typed copies
    - Phillips, Eleanor M., 1948-51 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      11 ALS, 3 cards
    - Playter, Phyllis
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: John Cowper Powys, Box 6, folder 96
    - Pollard, Ruth, 1924-45 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      6 letters. Typed copies with carbon copies
    - Powys, John Cowper & Phyllis Playter, 1929-52 (Box 4, Folder 48-53)
      64 letters & 40 postcards
    - Powys, John Cowper & Phyllis Playter, 1929-52 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
      104 letters. Typed copies
    - Powys, John Cowper & Phyllis Playter, 1929-52 (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
      89 letters. Carbon copies
    - Savage, Henry, 1946-52 (Box 5, Folder 58-59)
      65 letters. Typed copies
    - Savage, Henry, 1946-52 (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
      65 letters. Carbon copies
    - Shaw, George Bernard, 1950 Aug 27 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Sinclair, Frederick, 1949 Feb (Box 5, Folder 63)
      1 letter. On the verso of a letter from Dorothy Shirley to Dorothy Richardson
    - Suckow, Ruth & Ernest, 1935-51 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      7 letters. Typed copies
    - Taylor, Mr., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Tomkinson, Grace, 1947-9 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      2 letters. With 2 sets of typed copies, including a typescript of a letter of 1946 Nov 27, of which the original is wanting
    - Wells, H. G., 1910-19 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - White, Mr., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - LETTERS TO DOROTHY RICHARDSON FROM:
    - Unidentified, [Christmas] (Box 5, Folder 69)
      (signed Rachel, Edwin, Alexander, John)
    - Allinson, M., 1923 Dec 24 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      1 postcard
    - Ashton, J.H., 1951 Aug 27 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Bryher, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Church, Richard, 1936 Mar 12 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Committee of the Exhibition of Western Revolutionary Art, 1926 Jan 25 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      1 letter with "An address to all Western European and American organizations..."
    - Desborough, Ethel, Lady, 1919 Apr 16 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Donnelly, Dorothy M., 1953 Dec 10 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Doolittle, Hilda (HD), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      1 letter & 1 postcard. With 2 typed copies of the letter
    - Ellis, Amabel Williams, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Flecker, W.H., 1934 Oct 29 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Gale, Frances, 1923 Jul 1 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Grad, Mrs. Veronica, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 81)
      ("Amabel" of Pilgrimage) 1 letter & 1 postcard
    - Hale, Jessie A.
      See: Letters by Others, Box 7, folder 114
    - Hemingway, Ernest, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 82)
      2 letters. With photocopies
    - Houghton, Claude, 1948-52 (Box 6, Folder 83)
      4 letters. Typed copies, with carbon copies
    - [Empty folder] (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Huxley, Aldous Leonard, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Iyengar, K.R. Srinivasa, 1949 Feb 23 (Box 6, Folder 86)
      1 letter. With a typed copy
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy, 1956 Feb 1 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Kumar, Shiv K., 1952 Oct 15 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Marrian, Pauline, 1952 Nov 17 (Box 6, Folder 89)
      1 letter. Typed copy
    - Mase, Georgina, 1952 Dec 14 (Box 6, Folder 89a)
    - Moore, George, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 90)
      2 letters & 1 postcard
    - Morgan, Louise, 1951 Jul 4 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Nichols, Robert Malise Bowyer, 1917 Oct 23 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Nuhn, Ferner, 1952 Mar 1 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Odle, Alan, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Odle, Rose, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1930-52 (Box 6, Folder 96-97)
      76 letters. With a letter to Rose Odle, Aug 5
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1930-52 (Box 6, Folder 98-99)
      76 letters. Typed copies
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1930-52 (Box 6, Folder 100-101)
      76 letters. Carbon copies
    - Rodker, John, 1929 Jul 26 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Shaw, George Bernard, 1929 Jan 2 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Sinclair, Frederick, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 104)
      3 letters
    - Sokoloff, Olga, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 105)
      1 postcard. With a copy in Dorothy Richardson's hand
    - Trotter, Wilfred, 1930 Dec 16 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Walpole, Sir Hugh, 1940 Mar 20 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Wells, Amy Catherine (Robbins), 1902 Apr 8 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - LETTERS BY OTHERS, MOSTLY ABOUT DOROTHY RICHARDSON:
    - Bozman, E.F.
      - Letter to Rose Odle, 1963 Aug 21 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Davison, Peter H.
      - Letter to Norman Holmes Pearson, 1957 Oct 25 (Box 7, Folder 110)
        With a typed copy of a letter from Pearson to Davison, 1957 Oct 28
    - Elliott, Bernice
      - Letter to Rose Odle, 1957 Oct 26 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Farrar, John Chipman
      - Letter to Norman Holmes Pearson, 1957 Sep 3 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Grad, Mrs. Veronica ("Amabel" of Pilgrimage)
      - 7 letters and postcards to Rose Odle (Box 7, Folder 113)
        With Rose Odle's account of her meeting with Mrs. Grad immediately after Dorothy Richardson's death in 1957 and of Mrs. Grad's letters describing details of Dorothy Richardson's early life and identifying characters in the novels.
    - Hale, Jessie A.
      - 2 letters to "Goobie", 1952-3 (Box 7, Folder 114)
        [i.e. Dorothy Richardson]
      - Letter to Mrs. Rose Odle, 1957 Aug 27 (Box 7, Folder 115)
        With a typed copy
    - Jones, E.B.C.
      - 2 letters to Rose Odle, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Kumar, Shiv K.
      - 2 letters to Rose Odle, 1957-8 (Box 7, Folder 117)
        With typed copies of letters from Dorothy Richardson to Kumar
    - McDowell, David
      - 2 letters to Norman Holmes Pearson, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Odle, Alan
      - Letter to [Bryher?], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 119)
        With 3 p. of drawings
      - Greeting card for [Hilda Doolittle? (HD)], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 120)
      - Letter to [John Cowper Powys?], n.d. (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - Odle, Rose
      - Letter to Leon Edel, 1957 Nov 21 (Box 7, Folder 122)
      - 7 letters and 3 postcards to Horace & Marya Gregory, 1962-64 (Box 7, Folder 123)
      - 2 letters to Patrick Gregory, 1963-64 (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - Playter, Phyllis
      - Letter to Rose Odle, 1957 Jun 19 (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - Pollard, Ruth
      - Letter to Rose Odle, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - Smith, Molly Mitchell
      - Letter to Rose Odle, 1963 Sep 9 (Box 7, Folder 127)
        With MS notes, 1 p.
    - Woolford, F.E.
      - Letter to Leon Edel, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 128)
        With 2 typed lists
- Writings, Series II; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Contents: Miscellaneous, arranged alphabetically by the first word of the entry assigned; Manuscripts and typescripts of Dorothy Richardson's works; Short stories and articles, arranged by title; Novels, arranged by title; Manuscripts and typescripts of works about Dorothy Richardson, arranged alphabetically by author. The first group, 'Miscellaneous', contains items belonging to Dorothy Richardson such as notebooks, notecards, and an excerpt from a novel by H. G. Wells, which do not fit neatly into any specific category. In describing Dorothy Richardson's shorter works, an attempt has been made to distinguish among short stories, literary essays, and book reviews: the purely fictional works are merely listed with no comment; essays usually have a brief description of their subject matter, except in such instances where the subject is fairly clear from the title; and book reviews list the author and title of the book(s) being reviewed. In instances where it is known, publication information is given. In some cases it was clear from clippings in Series III that a particular article was published in the Saturday Review, but it was impossible to ascertain the volume, number, or date of publication.
  - MISCELLANEOUS
    - Address books: 2 small notebooks, one containing addresses up to 1945, the other with addresses from 1945 onwards., [ca. 1945] (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Appointment card for Dorothy Richardson at St. Mary's Church, Putney [1889] with much later note by Dorothy Richardson (on verso) about an exhibition of Alan Odle's drawings., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Notebook containing lists of Dorothy Richardson's correspondents, corrections of Pilgrimage, and miscellaneous notes. (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Notecards: autograph MS outlines of Dorothy Richardson's schedule of publication for the years 1913, 1914, and 1915. 3 cards., 1913-5 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - POEMS & FRAGMENTS: autograph MS list of her poems, written on the back of a postcard., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Wells, Herbert George THE HISTORY OF MR. POLLY: typescript (extract from the first chapter) 1 p. On verso: "Wells" in Dorothy Richardson's hand. (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - MSS & TYPESCRIPTS OF RICHARDSON'S SHORT STORIES AND ARTICLES
    - ABOUT PUNCTUATION: typescript (2 carbon copies) 9, 9 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 135)
      Published in Adelphi, vol. 1, no. 11, April 1924, p. 990-996.
    - ACROSS THE YEAR: typescript 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - ADVENTURE FOR READERS: typescript (carbon) 9 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 137)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, vol. 22, no. 23, July 1939, p. 45-52.
    - AUGUST: typescript 3 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 138)
      Published in Saturday Review, vol. 114, no. 2962, August 3, 1912, p. 142.
    - AUTHORS & READERS: autograph MS drafts 3 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - BEGINNINGS: typescript, signed, with additions and corrections in the hand of the author. 6l. Accompanied by the corrected page proof of the essay. 4 p. (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - BIRTH CONTROL. [THE] NEW MACHIAVELLI: autograph MS and typescript notes about H. G. Wells' The New Machiavelli 5 p. (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - BORED WIVES - WHERE IS MISS JAMESON'S SUBURBIA?: typescript (carbon) review of S. Jameson's Bored Wives 6 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - THE CONFLICT: typescript 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 143)
    - DANS LA BISE: typescript 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 144)
      Published in Saturday Review.
    - DATA FOR SPANISH PUBLISHER: typescript and 2 carbons of an autobiography 11, 10, 10 p. (Box 8, Folder 145)
      Published in The London Magazine, vol. 6, no. 6, June 1959, p. 14-19.
    - DECEMBER: typescript 3 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 146)
    - DUSK: typescript 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 147)
    - EN PAYS DE VAUD: typescript 6 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 148)
    - THE END OF THE WINTER: typescript (carbon) 5 p. (Box 8, Folder 149)
    - [Essay on H. G. Wells]: autograph MS fragment of an essay, canceled 1 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 150)
      On verso: fragment of a piece of fictional writing.
    - EXCURSION: typescript (carbon) 9 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 151)
      Published in English Story: Sixth Series, 1945, p. 107-112.
    - GRUYERES: typescript 6 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 152)
    - HAVEN: typescript (carbon) 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 153)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, vol. 43, no. 84, August 1944, p. 97-105.
    - HAY-TIME: typescript 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 154)
    - HIBBERT: autograph MS essay about Lucien Laberthonniere and religious faith 2 p. (Box 8, Folder 155)
    - THE HOLIDAY: typescript 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 156)
    - JANSENISM: autograph MS draft, heavily revised and corrected 6 [i.e. 7] p. (Box 8, Folder 157)
    - JOURNEY TO PARADISE: typescript (carbon) 11 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 158)
      Published in Fortnightly Review, New Series, vol. 123, no. 735, March 1, 1928, p. 407-414.
    - LITERARY ESSAYS: autograph MS draft of an essay on her development as a writer 2 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 159)
      With photocopies.
    - LODGE NIGHT: typescript (carbon) 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 160)
    - MARCH: typescript (carbon) 2 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 161)
    - THE MASTERY OF LIFE: autograph MS draft of a review of G. T. Wrench's The Mastery of Life 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 162)
    - MR. CLIVE BELL'S PROUST: typescript (carbon) review 7 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 163)
      Published in New Adelphi, vol. 2, no. 2, December 1928 - February 1929, p. 160-162.
    - NICOLAS BERDYAEV IN DILEMMA: typescript signed, with one autograph MS correction 1 p.l., 6 p. (Box 8, Folder 164)
    - [Notes on Kierkegaard]: autograph MS draft of the conclusion of an article 1 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 165)
    - NOVELS: typescript (carbon) of a review of A. Huxley's Eyeless in Gaza and T. Beresford's Break of Day 3 [i.e.4] p. (Box 8, Folder 166)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, Winter, 1936-37, p. 188-189.
    - OLD AGE: typescript (carbon) 3 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 167)
    - PEACH HARVEST: typescript 6 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 168)
    - THE PINK OUTLOOK (WELLS & WOMEN): autograph MS notes, 1 p., 1924 Sep (Box 8, Folder 169)
    - THE PROPHET OF BECOMING: autograph MS notes, possibly a translation of some thoughts of Georg Britting 1 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 170)
    - THE RAMPANT METAPHOR: autograph MS notes and drafts 3 p. (Box 8, Folder 171)
    - A SCULPTOR OF DREAMS: typescript (carbon) of a re-view of Mrs. H. A. Foster's Studies in Dreams 7 p. (Box 8, Folder 172)
      Published in Adelphi, vol. 2, no. 5, October 1924, p. 422-427.
    - SECRET OF ENGLISH CLASS DIALECTS: autograph MS notes and drafts 2 p. (Box 8, Folder 173)
    - A STRANGER ABOUT: typescript (2 carbon copies) 8, 8 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 174)
      Published in English Story: Ninth Series, 1949, p. 90-94.
    - STRAWBERRIES: typescript (carbon) 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 175)
      Published in Saturday Review, vol. 113, no. 2956, June 22, 1912, p. 778-779.
    - SUNDAY: typescript (carbon) 6 p. (Box 8, Folder 176)
      Published in Arts & Letters, New Series, vol. 2, no. 3, Summer 1910, p. 113-115.
    - A SUSSEX AUCTION: typescript 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 177)
    - A SUSSEX CARRIER: typescript 5 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 178)
    - SUSSEX PERIOD: autograph MS notes on her artistic development and the feminist movement 8 p. (Box 8, Folder 179)
    - A TALK ABOUT TALKING: typescript (carbon) of a review of T. Pear's The Psychology of Conversation 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 180)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, vol. 23, no. 27 [i.e.28], December 1939, p. 286-288.
    - THREE POEMS (Sussex; Discovery; Barbara): typescript 2 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 181)
      Published in Poetry: A Magazine of Verse, vol. 27, no. 2, November 1925, p. 67-69.
    - A VILLAGE COMPETITION: typescript 6 p, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 182)
    - VISIT: typescript (carbon) 13 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 183)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, vol. 46, no. 97, September 1945, p. 173-181.
    - VISITOR: typescript (carbon) 9 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 184)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, vol. 46, no. 97, September 1945, p. 167-172.
    - THE VOICE OF ONE CRYING IN THE WILDERNESS: autograph. MS essay describing her impressions of H. G. Wells' voice 3 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 185)
      With a typed copy and carbon, 2 p.
    - WANTED: THE PLAY-SPIRIT: typescript (carbon) 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 186)
      Published in Plain Talk, July 1913, p. 5-6.
    - WELCOME: typescript 4 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 187)
      Published in Saturday Review, vol. 113, no. 2951, May 18, 1912, p, 620-621.
    - THE WIND: typescript 4 p. (Box 8, Folder 188)
    - WOMEN AND THE FUTURE, A TREMBLING OF THE VEIL BEFORE THE ETERNAL MYSTERY OF "LA GIACONDA": typescript (carbon) essay on the attitudes of various writers toward women 8 p. (Box 8, Folder 189)
      Published in Vanity Fair, vol. 22, no. 2, April 1924, p. 39-40.
    - WOMEN IN THE ARTS: typescript (carbon) essay discussing the problems of being a woman artist 9 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 190)
      Published in Vanity Fair, vol. 24, no. 3, May 1925, p. 47, 100.
    - THE WORLD SET FREE: autograph MS draft of a review of H. G. Wells' The World Set Free 1 p., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 191)
      With a later draft headed A Voice Crying in the Wilderness, 2 p. (not to be confused with her The Voice of One Crying in the Wilderness - cf. Series II. Box 3, folder 22)
    - YEATS OF BLOOMSBURY: typescript (carbon) of an article describing the time she and Yeats both inhabited Woburn Way 9 p. (Box 8, Folder 192)
      Published in Life and Letters To-day, vol. 21, no. 20, April 1939, p. 60-66.
  - MSS AND TYPESCRIPTS OF DOROTHY RICHARDSON'S NOVELS
    - MARCH MOONLIGHT
      - Miscellaneous autograph MS notes and drafts, including some passages which were apparently deleted from the published text of the novel 9 p. (Box 9, Folder 193)
        Sketches by Alan Odle are on the verso of two of the pages.
      - Autograph MS draft of portions of chapter 4, revised and corrected 10 p. (Box 9, Folder 194)
        (numbered 2 75; 3 76; 5 78; 6; 6 79; 80; 81; 86; 88).
      - Typescript (carbon) 161 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 195-196)
        Published in her Pilgrimage, London J.M. Dent & Sons Ltd [1967], vol. 4.
    - POINTED ROOFS
      - Autograph MS, signed, with many additions and corrections 284 p. [i.e. 334 p.] (Box 9, Folder 197-200)
        Published by Duckworth & Co, London, 1915.
  - MSS AND TYPESCRIPTS OF WORKS ABOUT DOROTHY RICHARDSON
    - Chevalley, Abel
      - LE ROMAN ANGLAIS, HISTOIRE ET DESTINS: typescript (extract from an article in Vient de paraître, July 1925) 3 p. (Box 9, Folder 201)
    - Elliott, Bernice
      - MEMORIES OF DOROTHY RICHARDSON: typescript (with 2 carbons) 13, 13, 13 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 202)
      - FOREWORD, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 203)
        [by an unidentified author]: typescript 1 p.
    - Hale, Jessie A.
      - DATA ABOUT THE EARLY LIFE OF DOROTHY M. RICHARDSON: typescript drafts 7 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 204)
    - Johnson, Pamela Hansford
      - [Statement about Dorothy Richardson]: autograph MS, dated April 25, 1963 1 p. With a typed copy., 1963 Apr 25 (Box 9, Folder 205)
    - Kirkaldy, Peggy
      - D.M. RICHARDSON: typescript 6 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 206)
    - Lawrence, Margaret
      - WE WRITE AS WOMEN: typescript (extract) 2 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 207)
    - Marrian, Pauline
      - DOROTHY RICHARDSON: typescript (2 copies) 3, 3 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 208)
    - Odle, Rose
      - ANTHOLOGY. SELECTIONS FROM THE WRITINGS OF DOROTHY M. RICHARDSON: typescript 2 [i.e.3] p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 209)
      - PILGRIMAGE. LIST OF CORRECTIONS: typescript 4 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 210)
      - SOME MEMORIES OF DOROTHY M. RICHARDSON AND ALAN ODLE: typescript (2 copies) 22, 20 p. (Box 9, Folder 211)
    - Powys, John Cowper
      - DOROTHY RICHARDSON: autograph MS 33 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 212)
      - NOTES AT THE TIME OF FIRST MEETING: typescript 5 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 213)
    - Prescott, Joseph
      - A PRELIMINARY CHECKLIST OF THE PERIODICAL PUBLICATIONS OF DOROTHY M. RICHARDSON: typescript 7 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 214)
    - [Savage, Henry?]
      - A LAST KICK: typescript (extract) p. 64-67., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 215)
      - THE RECEDING SHORE: typescript (extract) 1 p. With an airplane ticket. Ticket missing 5 Jan 1979., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 216)
- Special Files, Series III; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Contents: Clippings of articles by Dorothy Richardson, arranged alphabetically by title; publication information is provided when known; Clippings about Dorothy Richardson, arranged chronologically; Clippings about Dorothy Richardson's works, arranged alphabetically by title of work, then chronologically within each folder; Clippings about other people connected with Dorothy Richardson, arranged alphabetically by name of person; Legal agreements, arranged alphabetically by name(s) of contractor(s); Photographs, arranged loosely according to subject matter.
  - CLIPPINGS OF ARTICLES BY DOROTHY RICHARDSON
    - ABOUT BOOKS, Plain Talk, July 1913, p. 13-14., 1913 Jul (Box 10, Folder 217)
    - ABOUT PUNCTUATION, Adelphi, vol. 1, no. 11, p. 990-996., 1924 Apr (Box 10, Folder 218)